<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="alexander.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="core_edit.css"?>
<root>
    <anchor ref="c0">
        <p type="lines" c="1.3.4">When the child (Alexander) was born and came into the light, he
            cried and said: <q>In my 40th year I will return to you again, mother!</q></p>
    </anchor>
    <anchor ref="c1">
        <p type="lines" c="4.103.3">Having come near (the Amazons') city, (Alexander) stopped there
            with his retinue. And waiting there, he sent them a letter containing the following:
                <q>Alexander, king of kings, sends to Talistris, the Amazon queen …</q></p>
    </anchor>
    <anchor ref="c2">
        <p type="lines" c="4.103.16">Then Queen Talistris received Alexander's letter, read it, and
            wrote a letter back to Alexander as follows:</p>
    </anchor>
    <anchor ref="c3">
        <p type="lines" c="4.103.23">If you wish to learn how we abide, let us show you in this
            letter:</p>
    </anchor>
    <anchor ref="c4">
        <p type="lines" c="4.103.46">If you kill us, you will not achieve any fame, for you will
            have killed women.</p>
    </anchor>
    <anchor ref="c5">
        <p type="lines" c="4.103.47">If you will come to us in battle, send to us quickly: we will
            meet you at the foot of the mountains!</p>
    </anchor>
    <anchor ref="c6">
        <p type="lines" c="4.103.50">Alexander read the letter before all his horsemen. And
            Alexander laughed greatly at it and had a letter written containing the following:</p>
    </anchor>
    <anchor ref="c7">
        <p type="lines" c="4.103.59">If you do not want to perish, consider well your lives and give
            us tribute and send us some of your horsewomen, so that we may see them and receive them
            with joy and honor them well.</p>
    </anchor>
    <anchor ref="c8">
        <p type="lines" c="4.103.64">Then Queen Talistris sent Alexander … precious gifts and a
            letter containing the following:</p>
    </anchor>
    <anchor ref="c9">
        <p type="lines" c="4.103.70">A rumor has come to our ears … that, having taken all the
            world, you want to fight a women's army … It is not fitting for you to fight us.</p>
    </anchor>
    <anchor ref="c10">
        <p type="lines" c="4.103.75">For if you destroy us, you will achieve little honor; if we
            destroy you, this will be a great disgrace for you.</p>
    </anchor>
    <anchor ref="c11">
        <p type="lines" c="4.103.84">Have mercy on us and accept the small offerings of your
            faithful servants and write back with hope (for us) soon!</p>
    </anchor>
    <anchor ref="c12">
        <p type="lines" c="4.103.106">Alexander laughed … and said (to Ptolemy): <q>Even if you are
                the general of (all) my forces, (a single) one of those women can overcome
            you.</q></p>
    </anchor>

</root>
