<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="RII_xvii-order.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="RII_xvii-order.css"?>
<root>
   <title type="supplied">Lay of the Emir: 17th-c. reordering by Muscovite epitomizer</title>
   <p pageref="342v">
      <page>Pog 342v</page> A Tale of Bygone Times and Brave Men, about the Boldness and about the
      Bravery and about the Might of the Glorious Devgenij</p>
   <anchor ref="α">
      <p pageref="342v">There was a widow of royal family, and she devoted herself to salvation; she
         was never away from church. And she had three sons, splendid and handsome; with their
         mother’s prayer they were brave in all that they did. The widow also had a daughter,
         splendid and beautiful in the beauty of her face.</p>
      <p pageref="342v">And Amir the tsar of the Arab land heard of the maiden’s beauty and
         assembled his force, full large, and went to attack the Greek land for the sake of this
         maiden’s beauty. And Amir the tsar came to the house of the widow and carried off the fair
            <page>343</page> maiden by his cunning; he was invisible to everyone in the Greek land,
         save that one old woman of the house saw him. At the time her mother was in God’s church;
         the sons were hunting in another country.</p>
      <p pageref="343">And the widow came from God’s church and did not find her fair daughter and
         began to question her slaves in her house about her fair daughter. And all the slaves of
         her house said to her: <q>We do not know, Lady, about your fair daughter.</q> Save that one
         old woman of the house had seen and told her mistress, the widow: <q>Lady, Amir the tsar of
            the Arab land came and stole away your daughter, our mistress, by his cunning, and he
            was invisible in our land.</q>
      </p>
      <p pageref="343">And on hearing this from her slave the widow began to tear the hair from her
         head and [to tear] her face, and she began to weep over her fair <page>343v</page> daughter
         and said: <q>Woe is me, wretched widow. If my children had been at home, they would have
            gone and pursued Amir the tsar and taken away their sister.</q>
      </p>
      <p pageref="343v">After a little while her children came home, and seeing their mother weeping
         they began to question their mother: <q>Tell us, our mother, who has insulted you, whether
            a tsar or a prince of this city? If you have been insulted, we shall not live.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="a">
      <p pageref="343v">Their mother said to them: <q>My dear children, I have not been insulted by
            anyone of this city, rather you have had at home one sister, and she has now been stolen
            away by the hands of Amir the tsar of the Arabian land. And he has torn out my heart by
            the roots and pierced me like a lifeless reed. And now I adjure you, my beloved
            children, that you fail not to hearken to my command. Go and pursue Amir the tsar and
            take away your fair little sister;</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="b">
      <p pageref="343v">
         <q>if your sister <page>Tit 172</page> you do not recover, do you thus lay down your heads
            for your little sister, and I (shall lament) all of you since I shall have no
            children.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="c">
      <p pageref="172">Her sons said: <q>Our mother, do not be distressed and do not worry about
            this; quickly give us your prayer and we shall cover our way.</q> They girt themselves
         with their weapons</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="d">
      <p pageref="172">and mounted their horses and went like gold-winged hawks;</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e">
      <p pageref="172">their horses seemed to fly beneath them. They reached the borders of the
         Saracen land;</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="fbis">
      <p pageref="172">they came upon a Saracen standing guard.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="g">
      <p pageref="172">And the brothers began to question him: <q>Tell us, Saracen, how far to the
            abode of your Amir the tsar?</q> But the Saracen drew his sword; he ran upon them
         boldly, thinking them deserters, not knowing their boldness.</p>
      <p pageref="172">And the youngest brother sprang, grasped the Saracen by the throat and
         dragged him to his brothers and wished to slay him. The eldest brother said to them: <q>My
            dear brothers! Why should we defile our swords upon a Saracen? Let us defile them upon
            Amir the tsar himself, – he is guilty!</q> This Saracen they tied <page>172v</page> to a
         tree on a mountain.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="10">
      <p pageref="172v">And they themselves went their way</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="11">
      <p pageref="172v">and came upon many guards of Amir the tsar</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="f">
      <p pageref="172v">beyond a great river called Bagrjanica;</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="11bis">
      <p pageref="172v">they were three thousand in number. The brothers saw the great guard of Amir
         the tsar and the eldest brother said: <q>My brothers, it were well to ride together against
            the guards of Amir the tsar.<q> But the middle brother said: </q>My dear brothers, the
            guard of Amir the tsar is large; let us divide in three.</q>
      </p>
      <p pageref="172v">The eldest brother (went) on the right hand, the middle in the center, the
         youngest on the left hand; they sprang upon the men of Amir the tsar and began to strike
         them as good mowers mow grass: some they bound, some they slaughtered, and they drove them
         among them like good shepherds sheep. They chased them and killed them; only three men did
         they spare to lead them to Amir the tsar.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="gbis">
      <p pageref="172v">And they began to question them: <q>Tell us, Saracens, does Amir the tsar
            dwell in your city or not?</q>
      </p>
      <p pageref="172v">The Saracens replied: <q>Dear brothers, Amir <page>173</page> our tsar
            dwells outside the city; he dwells seven leagues from the city. He has many tents; one
            tent contains many thousands, strong and brave; one will attack a hundred.<q> And the
               brothers said to the Saracens: </q>If we feared not God, we should long ago have put
            you to death. But we ask you, that we may not be tempted. Tell us, what sort of tent has
            Amir the tsar?</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="h=37bis">
      <p pageref="173">And the Saracens said: <q>Amir the tsar has a dark-red tent, green at the
            base; the tent is plated with gold and silver and pearl, and adorned with precious
            stones. His brother has a dark-blue tent, green at the base; his tent is likewise
            adorned. Other tents there are, full many; in them reside warriors. They receive from
            the tsar each year a revenue of one thousand and of two, and are strong and brave; one
            will attack a hundred.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="i=45-48bis">
      <p pageref="173">The brothers let them go to Amir the tsar and said to them: <q>Go, take word
            to Amir the tsar, lest Amir the tsar say, ’like robbers the brothers came and slew
            me’.</q> The Saracens (were) glad to be let go, and went <page>173v</page> to take word
         to Amir the tsar.</p>
      <p pageref="173v">And when Amir the tsar heard, he was afraid and said to his warriors: <q>My
            dear brothers, strong warriors, I had this night a dream that three hawks were beating
            me with their wings: they all but laid wounds on my body: it means that the brothers
            have come and will begin to quarrel with me.</q>
      </p>
      <p pageref="173v">At that moment the brothers reached the tent of Amir the tsar and began to
         shout, calling out Amir the tsar:</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="8">
      <p pageref="173v">
         <q>Tell us, Amir the tsar, have you not guards posted on the way? We reached the tent
            without any resistance. But now tell us – may the bear wound you – you came and have
            stolen away our little sister like a thief. If we had chanced at home, you could not
            have escaped (with) our little sister, but would have died a wretched death and all your
            land would be in thrall to us.</q></p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="9">
      <p pageref="173v"><q>Now tell us, where have you put our little sister?</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="12">
      <p pageref="173v">And Amir the tsar answered them:</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="13">
      <p pageref="173v">
         <q>My dear brothers, you see that mountain, great and fair? There (were slain many honored)
            women and fair maidens. And there <page>174</page> was your sister slain because she had
            not done my will.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="14">
      <p pageref="174">The brothers said: <q>Dear brothers, let us go to that fair mountain and see
            the dead maiden: let us take her; then we shall deal with Amir the tsar.</q> They
         mounted their horses and went up</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="15">
      <p pageref="174">and saw on the mountain many women and fair maidens slain.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="16">
      <p pageref="174">They began to seek their sister</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="18">
      <p pageref="174">and found one maiden very fair and began to shed tears over her, believing
         she was their sister. But their youngest brother said: <q>She is not our sister and not our
            kin.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="21">
      <p pageref="174">The brothers mounted their horses and were loudly singing the angelic hymn to
         the Lord: <q>Blessed be the Lord our God; teach our hands to battle, our fingers to
            struggle. Let us remember, brothers, the word of our mother: one day we were born, one
            day we too shall die; at the bidding of our mother let us lay down our heads for our
            little sister.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="23bis">
      <p pageref="174">And they charged the tent of Amir the tsar and lifted the tent on their
         lances, calling out Amir the tsar.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="j">
      <p pageref="174">But Amir the tsar said to them: <q>My dear <page>174v</page> brothers, get
            you gone from this tent and cast lots among you to see which one of you the lot calls to
            fight with me. If you overcome me, take your little sister. If I overcome you, it is my
            pleasure to slay all of you.</q>
      </p>
      <p pageref="174v">And the brothers rode off from the tent and began to cast lots; they cast
         the first time and the lot called the youngest to go to battle. And the brothers cast lots
         a second time, but it was for the youngest to go. Because he is not strong, they cast a
         third time out of pity for their brother, but it came out for the youngest brother to go to
         battle. And the brothers said to the youngest brother: <q>Since you came forth from our
            mother’s womb together with your little sister, you and your sister cannot be
            separated.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="2bis">
      <p pageref="174v">And the brothers began to arm the youngest brother. And where the brothers
         were standing, that place shines like the sun, but where Amir the tsar is arming, that
         place is dark as darkness.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="2">
      <p pageref="174v">The brothers raise the angelic hymn to God: <q>Sire, suffer not Thy
               <page>175</page> creature to be the sport of pagans, lest the pagans rejoice, having
            dishonored a Christian maiden.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="5">
      <p pageref="175">And mounting their horses they came down, as did Amir the tsar. They began to
         hack with sabers and they smote one another with swords and with lances.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="4">
      <p pageref="175">But when the Saracens and the many warriors saw this, the boldness of the
         youngest brother, they said to Amir the tsar: <q>Great Lord, give them back their sister
            and make peace with them, for lo! their youngest brother has conquered your strength. If
            they join together, all our land will be in thrall to them.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="6">
      <p pageref="175">The youngest brother, grasping his mace, came up behind Amir the tsar and
         smote him between the shoulders with the mace and knocked him off his horse and grasped him
         by the hair and dragged him to his brothers. All the Saracens said loudly to Amir the tsar:
            <q>Give back, Lord and Tsar, their sister, lest they destroy you utterly.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="7">
      <p pageref="175">And Amir the tsar said to them: <q>Have mercy (on me), dear brothers</q>;</p>
   </anchor>

   <anchor ref="25">
      <p pageref="175"><q>this day I shall receive holy baptism for love of that maiden,</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="26">
      <p pageref="175">
         <q>that I may be your <page>175v</page> brother-in-law.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="23">
      <p pageref="175v">The brothers said: <q>Brother, Amir the tsar, we have the power to slay you
            and we have the power to let you go. How can we give our sister to a slave? But now tell
            us, where is our sister?</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="9bis">
      <p pageref="175v">And Amir the tsar said to them tearfully: <q>Dear brothers! You see yon fair
            field? There stand many tents, and in them your sister resides.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="27">
      <p pageref="175v">
         <q>And wherever your sister walks, that place is strewn with golden coverlets, and her face
            is covered with a precious veil, while these her guards stand ever far from her
            tent.</q> Hearing this the brothers were joyful and galloped to her tent. And they went
         to their sister and found her sitting on a golden chair, her face covered with a precious
         veil.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="29=25-26bis+32bis">
      <p pageref="175v">Her brothers began to ask tearfully: <q>Tell us, our sister, of the boldness
            of Amir the tsar. If he has offended you with a single word, we shall cut off his head
            and carry it to the Greek land, that later he shall not boast, <q>I defiled a Christian
               maiden.</q>
         </q>
      </p>
      <p pageref="176">
         <page>176</page> But the maiden said to her brothers: <q>By no means, brothers, have any
            such thought in your mind. When I was stolen away by the hands of Amir the tsar (I) had
            twelve nurses. I told Amir the tsar of your boldness. And Amir the tsar always came to
            me once a month and looked upon me from afar. And he ordered his servants to cover my
            face and he would never enter the tent. Now I fear insult from the people and my kin
            because (I am) a captive.</q>
      </p>
      <p pageref="176">
         <q>I wish to speak to you, my brothers, and first I wish to adjure you by the prayer of our
            mother that you fail not to hearken to my command. If only Amir the tsar will truly
            renounce his faith and this day receive holy baptism, you will call no other
            brother-in-law, since he is in glory glorious, in strength strong, and in riches
            rich.</q> The brothers said to their sister: <q>Our mother’s prayer has joined you to
            Amir the tsar.</q>
      </p>
      <p pageref="176">At that time Amir the tsar collected three hundred camels and loaded them
         with precious Arab gold and gave them to the brothers <page>176v</page> as gifts for love
         of the maiden. Amir the tsar said to the brothers: <q>Have mercy on me, my dear brothers. I
            shall renounce my faith and this day receive holy baptism, that I may be your
            brother-in-law.</q>
      </p>
      <p pageref="176v">And the brothers said to Amir the tsar: <q>If you would be our
            brother-in-law, truly renounce your faith for love of this maiden, receive holy baptism,
            and go with us to the Greek land with your beloved maiden.</q> But Amir the tsar said: <q>Dear brothers, I shall not surrender shamefully,
               lest the Greeks say, ’they bring their brother-in-law like a captive.’ </q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="63bis">
      <p pageref="176v"> <q>I shall be called
            your brother-in-law; in great honor shall I come. I wish first to go and collect camels
            from all the land and load riches upon them. And I wish to assemble strong warriors, and
            whoever wishes to accept holy baptism with me,</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="31">
      <p pageref="176v">
         <q>and I shall come to you in the Greek land and I shall be called your brother-in-law and
            I shall be glorious and rich. Do not weary your horses; wait for me on the road.</q> And
         the brothers, taking their sister, went their way.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="64=[75]">
      <p pageref="176v">Amir the tsar, going to his mother <page>177</page> and to his brothers,</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="65=[75]">
      <p pageref="177">began to speak to them with guile, that they might not restrain him. And he
         said to his mother: <q>My dear mother, I went to the Greek land and captured for myself a
            beloved maiden. And her brothers came after me and began to fight with me. And one of
            them conquered my strength. If all three should join together, all our land would be in
            thrall to them.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="35bis">
      <p pageref="177">But his mother spoke to Amir the tsar angrily: (she began) to tear the hair
         from her head and (to tear) (her) face,</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="37">
      <p pageref="177">(and she said to him): <q>Why are you called tsar and have strong warriors
            serving you; they receive a revenue of the thousand and of two thousand. Go, assemble a
            great force and go to the Greek land and conquer the brothers and bring the beloved
            maiden here.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="65bis=[75]">
      <p pageref="177">And Amir the tsar said with guile to his mother: <q>Mother, I wish to do the
            same: to assemble warriors and go to attack the Greek land.</q> A brother of Amir the
         tsar said: <q>Let us go, Amir the tsar, after we have quickly assembled a force, that we
            may keep the brothers from the city with the beloved maiden.</q>
      </p>
      <p pageref="177">But Amir the tsar said to his brother: <q>Sit on my throne; I wish to go
            alone to attack the Greek land.</q> At that moment Amir the tsar sat <page>177v</page>
         his brother on his throne, while he himself assembled a great force and collected riches
         and camels from all that land, heaping precious Arab gold and costly stones upon them. The
         Saracens knew that men go not thus to battle but said nothing to him.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="68">
      <p pageref="177v">When Amir the tsar reached (the border of the Greek land, Amir the tsar
         said) to the Arabs:</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="69">
      <p pageref="177v">
         <q>My dear brothers, strong Arab warriors, who will go with me to attack the Greek
            land?</q></p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="63ter">
      <p pageref="177v"><q>{let him come with me.</q>}
      </p>
   </anchor><anchor ref="70">
      <p pageref="177v">There spoke from among them (one) Arab with twelve locks on his lips, and he
         said loudly to Amir the tsar: <q>Great Lord, Amir Tsar, there came from the Greek land to
            our Saracen land three youths. One of them conquered your strength; if all three should
            join together, all our land would be in thrall. Now you wish to attack the Greek land:
            they will destroy all utterly.</q> But Amir the tsar sent on ahead the camels loaded
         with riches, took with him a few of his warriors, and went to the Greek land.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="31bis">
      <p pageref="177v">The brothers came within fifty leagues of the Greek city <page>178</page>
         and halted. And their sister began to entreat them: <q>My dear brothers, do not bring me
            into great shame before men and before my kindred because I was stolen away by Amir the
            tsar. Wait for your brother-in-law.</q>
      </p>
      <p pageref="178">After a little time the tsar Amir came up to them with all his riches and
         with the camels loaded with gold and silver. And Amir the tsar said to them: <q>Glory to
            Thee, God, who hast been my benefactor. God hath found me worthy to look in the eyes of
            my brothers.</q> And the brothers said to Amir the tsar: <q>Slave of Christ, this very
            day be our brother-in-law.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="33">
      <p pageref="178">Two of the brothers, the eldest and the middle, (with) their little sister
         went to the city at night because of the people and reached the house of their mother. When
         their mother saw her two sons and her daughter, she said to them tearfully: <q>You have won
            your little sister but you have lost your brother.</q> But her sons said: <q>Rejoice,
            Mother, our youngest is together with our brother-in-law, with Amir the tsar. Now
            prepare a great wedding, since we have won a brother-in-law in glory glorious, and in
            strength strong and in riches rich; now we shall lead him to godly baptism.</q>
      </p>
      <p pageref="178">And taking the patriarch of the city with all the clergy they went to the
         river Euphrates and built <page>178v</page> a font (and) a host of people came forth from
         the city. At that time Amir the tsar came to the river Euphrates, and when the brothers saw
         Amir the tsar harassed (by the people),</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="57">
      <p pageref="178v">{readying his martial equipment.}</p>
   </anchor> <anchor ref="63">
      <p pageref="178v">{Looking at them, the emir said: <q>I will deceive the Arabs:</q>}</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="33bis">
      <p pageref="178v">
         taking Amir the tsar they quickly plunged him in
         godly baptism. And the patriarch himself baptized him: his godfather is the patriarch
         himself of the city. And they led him to the house of their mother and held a great
         wedding, very glorious, for three months. And then Amir the tsar built his own court and
         chambers and began to live with his wife.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="35">
      <p pageref="178v">After a little time, when the mother of Amir the tsar heard that Amir the
         tsar had been baptized and had renounced his faith for love of the maiden, she began to
         tear the hair from her head</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="40">
      <p pageref="178v">and assembled the forces of the Saracen land and said to them: <q>Who has
            the boldness to go to the Greek land (to your Lord, Amir the tsar, and bring him back
            from the Greek land with his beloved maiden?</q> And three Saracens said to her: <q>We
            shall go, Lady, to the Greek land) and bear (a letter) to Amir the tsar.</q> She gave
         them much gold and silver,</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="39">
      <p pageref="178v">and gave them three horses: (a horse) called Windflower, a second, Thunder,
         a third, Lightning, and (said): <q>If you are in the Greek land and see your lord, Amir the
            tsar, bring him forth from the Greek land and seat him on Windflower <page>179</page>
            and he will not be (harmed) by anyone. If you enter the Saracen land with your lord,
            Amir the tsar, and with the maiden, seat them on Thunder, and then all the Arabs of the
            Saracen land will hear. If you sit on Lightning, you will be in invisible in the Greek
            land.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="43">
      <p pageref="179">The Saracens took the three horses and the letter to Amir the tsar and went
         (their) way. And they reached the Greek city and halted outside the city in a secret place
         and mounted Lightning and were invisible in the Greek land.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="45">
      <p pageref="179">That night the queen, the fair wife (of Amir the tsar), had a dream and was
         afraid;</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="46">
      <p pageref="179">she told her brothers: <q>My dear brothers, I had this night a dream; at a
            certain moment a gold-winged falcon flew into my chamber and took (me by the hand and)
            carried me out of my chamber. Then three ravens flew up and attacked (the falcon) and
            the falcon let me go.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="47">
      <p pageref="179">The brothers assembled in the city all the seers and scribes and Pharisees
         and told of their sister’s dream. And they said to them:</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="48">
      <p pageref="179">
         <q>Your brother-in-law, newly-baptized Amir the tsar, at his mother’s bidding wishes to
            steal our fair lady from her chamber and flee to the Saracen land with your beloved
            little sister.</q></p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="47bis">
      <p pageref="179"><q>And the three ravens are Saracens, and they are in the city
               <page>179v</page> in a secret place; they have been sent after Amir the tsar with a
            letter from his mother.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="50">
      <p pageref="179v">The brothers went to Amir the tsar and began to accuse him.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="52">
      <p pageref="179v">But he swore by the Living God,</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="48bis">
      <p pageref="179v">so they took Amir the tsar and (went with him outside the city with) the
         scribes and Pharisees and found the three Saracens outside the city: they seized (them) and
         began to question them. And they swore to them that Amir the tsar knew not of it.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="75">
      <p pageref="179v">And they baptized them with godly baptism and they began to live at the
         abode of Amir the tsar. And taking their horses Amir the tsar bestowed them upon his
         brothers-in-law.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="33ter">
      <p pageref="179v">And then the scribes and Pharisees began to foretell the birth of
         Devgenij.</p>
      <p pageref="179v">And then the queen of Amir the tsar took fruit of male sex in her womb,</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="34">
      <p pageref="179v">and bore a son and they gave him the name of Akrit and baptized him with
         godly baptism and at the baptism they gave him the name of Devgenij. And the patriarch
         himself baptized him with godly baptism; his godmother is the queen.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="ω">
      <p pageref="179v">And Amir the tsar raised his son until he was ten years old.</p>
   </anchor>
</root>
