<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root xmlns:djb="http://www.obdurodon.org">
   <title type="supplied" pageref="16r">
      <page>16r</page>The Tale of How Devgenij Defeated Tsar Vasilij</title>
   <anchor ref="e1">
      <p pageref="16r">There was a certain tsar named Vasilij. And he became extremely angry,
         hearing of the daring and bravery of Devgenij, and he burned with the desire to capture him <G>
            <line n="970">Placeholder</line>
            <line n="971">Placeholder</line>
            <line n="972">Placeholder</line>
            <line n="973">Placeholder</line>
            <line n="974">Placeholder</line>
            <line n="975">Placeholder</line>
            <line n="976">Placeholder</line>
            <line n="977">Placeholder</line>
            <line n="978">Placeholder</line>
         </G>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e2">
      <p pageref="16r">for tsar Vasilij controlled all the land of Cappadocia.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e3">
      <p pageref="16r">And so he equipped his envoys and sent off an epistle to Devgenij and with
         feigned cordiality <page>16v</page> he wrote thus: <G>
            <line n="979">Placeholder</line>
         </G>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e4">
      <p pageref="16v">
         <q>Famed Devgenij! I very much want to see you. Do not hesitate now to visit my tsardom;
            your daring and courage have resounded over all the earth.</q>
         <G>
            <line n="980">Placeholder</line>
            <line n="981">Placeholder</line>
            <line n="982">Placeholder</line>
         </G>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e5">
      <p pageref="16v">
         <q>And I have come to love you with all my soul, and I wish to gaze upon your youth.</q>
         <G>
            <line n="983">Placeholder</line>
            <line n="984">Placeholder</line>
         </G>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e6">
      <p pageref="16v">They delivered the royal epistle to Devgenij, and Devgenij read it and
         understood that the epistle to him was false.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e7">
      <p pageref="16v">And Devgenij answered the tsar: <q>I am a simple man. Your royal highness has
            no need of anything from me,</q>
         <G>
            <line n="987">Placeholder</line>
            <line n="988">Placeholder</line>
            <line n="989">Placeholder</line>
            <line n="990">Placeholder</line>
            <line n="991">Placeholder</line>
         </G>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e8">
      <p pageref="16v">
         <q>but if you wish to see me, then take a small number of warriors with you and come to the
            River Euphrates.</q>
         <G>
            <line n="993">Placeholder</line>
            <line n="994">Placeholder</line>
         </G>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e9">
      <p pageref="16v">And then he ordered the envoys to say to their tsar: <q>If you wish to see
            me, an unworthy one, then take a few warriors with you, so as not to anger me, for youth
            brings many irrational acts with it.</q>
         <G>
            <line n="995">Placeholder</line>
            <line n="996">Placeholder</line>
            <line n="997">Placeholder</line>
            <line n="998">Placeholder</line>
            <line n="999">Placeholder</line>
            <line n="1000">Placeholder</line>
         </G>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e10">
      <p pageref="16v">
         <q>And if I should become angry and destroy your army, then you will not return alive!</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e11">
      <p pageref="16v">So they rode back and the envoy transmitted all that Devgenij had said. When
         he heard this, the tsar became extremely angry and sent the envoy back to Devgenij with the
         words:</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e12">
      <p pageref="16v">
         <q>My child! I do not wish to bring many warriors with me but only to admire your youth. I
            have nothing else in my heart.</q>
         <G>
            <line n="983">Placeholder</line>
            <line n="984">Placeholder</line>
         </G>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e13">
      <p pageref="16v">The royal envoy came to Devgenij and related all that had been said by the
         tsar and Devgenij answered him: <q>Tell your tsar this:</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e14">
      <p pageref="16v">
         <q>I do not fear <page>17r</page> you, tsar, nor your innumerable army, for I place my
            hopes on God.</q>
         <G>
            <line n="992">Placeholder</line>
         </G>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e15">
      <p pageref="17r">
         <q>I do not fear your evil plot but I say to you:</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e16">
      <p pageref="17r">
         <q>Come to the River Euphrates and you and I shall see each other.</q>
         <G>
            <line n="993">Placeholder</line>
            <line n="994">Placeholder</line>
         </G>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e17">
      <p pageref="17r">
         <q>If you come with a large force, then you will not rejoice in the fact that you rule, and
            your entire force will be destroyed.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e18">
      <p pageref="17r">And the envoy came to tsar Vasilij and related the words of Devgenij to
         him.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e19">
      <p pageref="17r">When he had heard this, the tsar immediately ordered his warriors summoned
         and having gathered them together, he moved off with that force to the place indicated by
         Devgenij. And having come to the River Euphrates, he set up his tents at some distance from
         the river. <G>
            <line n="1004">Placeholder</line>
            <line n="1005">Placeholder</line>
            <line n="1006">Placeholder</line>
         </G>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e20">
      <p pageref="17r">And the royal pavilion was enormous, bright red in color, and the top of it
         was sewn in pure gold; and inside the tent were quartered several thousand warriors. And
         the entire force of the tsar was covered: some in tents and other in sheltered places.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e21">
      <p pageref="17r">And the tsar stayed for six days on the river and he said to his voevodas:
            <q>Devgenij has found out something and contrived something against us for he himself
            intends to come with a large force.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e22">
      <p pageref="17r">And having said this, tsar Vasilij shook from fear.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e23">
      <p pageref="17r">And Devgenij sent a servant to the tsar with these words:</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e24">
      <p pageref="17r">
         <q>I am amazed that you have put forth so much labor <page>17v</page> on my account as I am
            nothing.</q>
         <G>
            <line n="1016">Placeholder</line>
            <line n="1017">Placeholder</line>
         </G>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e25">
      <p pageref="17v">
         <q>But I already told you of my custom: if you wish to meet me, then come with a small
            detachment.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e26">
      <p pageref="17v">
         <q>But you have gathered an enormous army thinking to defeat me, and that is
            disgraceful,</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e27">
      <p pageref="17v">
         <q>for my fame has gone throughout all the earth and to all lands. And so now do as you
            have intended to do.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e28">
      <p pageref="17v">Tsar Vasilij answered: <q>How dare you that you do not wish to submit to me,
            a tsar!</q> And fitting out his envoy, he sent him across the river and received
         Devgenij's envoy.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e29">
      <p pageref="17v">And the royal envoy came to transmit the royal words to Devgenij.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e30">
      <p pageref="17v">And Devgenij replied; <q>Tell your tsar: if he is relying on his great force,
            then I hope on God the Creator. And your force cannot compare with the might of God.</q>
         <G>
            <line n="1040">Placeholder</line>
            <line n="1041">Placeholder</line>
         </G>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e31">
      <p pageref="17v">
         <q>This day is nearly over but prepare for battle as of tomorrow morning, and come forth
            with your innumerable force and you will see the courage of an insignificant man who
            will appear before you; otherwise, I will be shamed for that which is not
            undertaken.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e32">
      <p pageref="17v">And the envoy of tsar Vasilij came back from Devgenij and told his words
            <page>18r</page> to the tsar.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e33">
      <p pageref="18r">The tsar quickly called his boyars and began taking counsel with them, and
         the magnates said to him: <q>What is your rule worth, tsar, if you are afraid of a single
            warrior – no forces are seen with him.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e34">
      <p pageref="18r">And Devgenij's envoy hurried across the river and told Devgenij all that had
         occurred with the tsar.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e35">
      <p pageref="18r">The next day at daybreak tsar Vasilij placed his forces and got ready to
         cross over the river</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e36">
      <p pageref="18r">to catch Devgenij like a hare in a trap.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e37">
      <p pageref="18r">Devgenij saw that tsar Vasilij had prepared an innumerable force, and he
         guessed that when he had crossed the river, he would surround him.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e38">
      <p pageref="18r">Furious, Devgenij said to his servants: <q>Join me in a little while, first I
            shall myself undertake some little labor and serve that tsar.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e39">
      <p pageref="18r">And having said these words, he propped himself up with his lance and leapt
         across the river like a strong falcon,</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e40">
      <p pageref="18r">and he shouted at the top of his lungs: <q>Where is this tsar Vasilij who
            wanted to see something of me?</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e41">
      <p pageref="18r">He shouted and immediately the warriors rushed at him, and he stuck his lance
         in the ground and rushed at the warriors with his bare sword.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e42">
      <p pageref="18r">And he galloped up and like a good mower cutting grass, the first time he
         galloped through, he defeated a thousand, then he came back and galloped through them
         again, and another <page>18v</page> thousand he defeated.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e43">
      <p pageref="18v">Tsar Vasilij saw the courage of Devgenij and with but a handful of his men
         fled.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e44">
      <p pageref="18v">Devgenij killed the remaining warriors and then bound up the remainder</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e45">
      <p pageref="18v">and shouted to his servants across the river: <q>Bring that swift horse of
            mine, the one called Wind.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e46">
      <p pageref="18v">They drove the horse over to him, he leapt onto it</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e47">
      <p pageref="18v">and Devgenij tore off and soon caught up to tsar Vasilij at the walls of his
         city,</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e48">
      <p pageref="18v">and he killed all the warriors who were with him, and took the tsar and three
         of his companions captive.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e49">
      <p pageref="18v">And he sent one of them into the city with the news. And he said to the
         citizens:</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e50">
      <p pageref="18v">
         <q>Come out to meet Devgenij; from this day on God has granted it that he will rule in your
            country.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e51">
      <p pageref="18v">When the heard this, they gathered together and came out to fight with him
         before the city, thinking that they would be fighting with an ordinary man.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e52">
      <p pageref="18v">And he sent a message to them, saying: <q>Put down your weapons and do not
            anger me.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e53">
      <p pageref="18v">They replied: <q>A single man cannot stand against our entire city.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e54">
      <p pageref="18v">When he heard their reply, Devgenij grew angry and rushed at them:</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e55">
      <p pageref="18v">some he killed, others he bound and handed over to his servants, and then he
         entered the city and began ruling there.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e56">
      <p pageref="18v">
         <page>19r</page> And he soon freed the captives, as it says in scripture: <q>The servant
            cannot be greater than his master, nor the son greater than his father.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e57">
      <p pageref="19r">
         <q>But I still have twelve years to live and now I wish to rest, I have seen many wars and
            victories in my youth,</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e58">
      <p pageref="19r">so spoke Devgenij to his father and he sat him on the royal throne and he
         summoned all his captives and gave them their freedom.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e59">
      <p pageref="19r">And he placed brands on the faces of Kanam and Ioakim and sent them to their
         native country.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="e60">
      <p pageref="19r">And he summoned all his relatives and shared in their great joy, and thus it
         continued for many days.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="edox">
      <p pageref="19r">Glory to our God now and forever and to the ages of ages! Amen.</p>
   </anchor>
</root>
