<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root xmlns:djb="http://www.obdurodon.org">
   <title type="supplied" pageref="181v">
      <page>181v</page>An Account of the Bravery of Devgenij: How Filipap and the Maiden Maksimijana
      Sent a Missive</title>
   <anchor ref="m1">
      <p pageref="181v">When Filipap and the maiden Maksimijana heard about the bravery and about
         the strength of Devgenij, they began to think how they might catch him</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m2">
      <p pageref="181v">like a hare in a net.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m3">
      <p pageref="181v">Filipap is brave and very strong and has great force;</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m4">
      <p pageref="181v">the maiden Maksimijana too has manly bravery, her army also.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m5">
      <p pageref="181v">And they advanced on glorious Devgenij and came and halted, before they
         reached the Greek city, on the river Euphrates.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m6">
      <p pageref="181v">And Maksimijana sent a guileful missive to glorious Devgenij:</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m7">
      <p pageref="181v">
         <q>O light, brilliant sun, glorious Devgenij, you rule among all of us, the brave and the
            strong,</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m8">
      <p pageref="181v">
         <q>like the month of May among all the months. In the month of May all heavenly and earthly
               <supplied>beauty</supplied> flowers; the trees put forth leaves and all heavenly
            beauty is created;</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m9">
      <p pageref="181v">
         <q>even so <page>182r</page> are you among us, glorious Devgenij.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m10">
      <p pageref="182r">
         <q>And we, glorious Devgenij, entreat you: play not the sluggard, bestir yourself;</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m11">
      <p pageref="182r">
         <q>come to us with no large force to the river Euphrates,</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m12">
      <p pageref="182r">
         <q>that we may see your youthfulness and bravery; there is no plot against you at all.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m13">
      <p pageref="182r">And glorious Devgenij read the missive</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m14">
      <p pageref="182r">and laughed</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m15">
      <p pageref="182r">and said to his father: <q>Father, I wish to go and see glorious and brave
            Filipap <supplied>and</supplied> the maiden Maksimijana,</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m16">
      <p pageref="182r">But his father said: <q>My dear child, glorious Devgenij, it is too early
            for you to think of battle;</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m17">
      <p pageref="182r">
         <q>you have not been in victorious battles, whereas Filipap in battles is strong and brave
            and the maiden Maksimijana is also, and he has a great force.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m18">
      <p pageref="182r">But Devgenij replied to the missive; he sent his favorite to them and
         said:</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m19">
      <p pageref="182r">
         <q>It is a great shame for me to go to fight against a woman,</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m20">
      <p pageref="182r">
         <q>but you, Filipap, old uncle, why have you come in great strength and led a host of
            innocent <supplied>people</supplied> against me?</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m21">
      <p pageref="182r">The maiden Maksimijana said: <q>Do not, brilliant sun, glorious Devgenij,
            have any such thought in your mind at all, since we have come see your youthfulness.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m22">
      <p pageref="182r">Day after day Devgenij was thinking how he might see the bravery
            <page>182v</page> of Filipap.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m23">
      <p pageref="182v">
         <supplied>And</supplied> he took a few of his favorites with him and asked a prayer from
         his father and from his mother: <q>Quickly bless me, father and mother mine.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m24">
      <p pageref="182v">
         <q>Have no concern at all over this; no wounds will be on my body from the hand of man,</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m25">
      <p pageref="182v">
         <q>since I put my trust in the strength of God and in your fatherly grace and that of my
            mother.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m26">
      <p pageref="182v">And mounting his horse he went on his way.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m27">
      <p pageref="182v">He reached the river Euphrates and stood on the bank</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m28">
      <p pageref="182v">and sent his favorites to Filipap and the maiden Maksimijana.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m29">
      <p pageref="182v">When Filipap saw that Devgenij had few soldiers,</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m30">
      <p pageref="182v">he began to chase them with his whole army.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m31">
      <p pageref="182v">When Devgenij saw his followers pursued,</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m32">
      <p pageref="182v">grasping his lance he planted his lance in the river and vaulted over on
         foot like a fierce falcon from a hunter's hand;</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m33">
      <p pageref="182v">he cried in a loud voice: <q>Give me my horse called Far'!</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m34">
      <p pageref="182v">And mounting his horse he began to chase them as a good mower to mow grass:
         in the first mowing a thousand, in the second another thousand he conquered;</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m35">
      <p pageref="182v">in the third mowing he overtook Filipap and smote him between the shoulders
         with his mace and knock him off his horse.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m36">
      <p pageref="182v">
         <supplied>When the maiden Maksimijana saw that Devgenij</supplied> was binding Filipap,</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m37">
      <p pageref="182v">she aimed her lance, wishing to run glorious Devgenij through
            <page>183r</page> from behind.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m38">
      <p pageref="183r">Seeing this, Devgenij grasped her lance and smote her with his lance and
         knocked her off her horse.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m39">
      <p pageref="183r">And having taken Filipap and the maiden Maksimijana,</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m40">
      <p pageref="183r">some he killed, while some he bound, and he drove them before him as a good
         shepherd drove sheep through a river.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m41">
      <p pageref="183r">At that time old uncle Filipap turned to Devgenij and said:</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m42">
      <p pageref="183r">
         <q>Gold-winged hawk, glorious Devgenij, you are glorious among us all, the strong and the
            brave. But there is yet a braver and a stronger than you in the world,</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m43">
      <p pageref="183r">
         <q>glorious Stratig, who has four sons; the rest of his army the earth cannot contain.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m44">
      <p pageref="183r">
         <q>And <supplied>he has</supplied> a daughter, the very glorious and beautiful Stratigovna;
            she has manly boldness and bravery,</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m45">
      <p pageref="183r">
         <q>while there is nothing fairer on earth than her fairness.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m46">
      <p pageref="183r">
         <q>Many tsars and kings, brave and strong, have come, but no one can take her, and to no
            one is she like in beauty and strength.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m47">
      <p pageref="183r">
         <q>But now spare my years; after a little let me go.</q> Glorious Devgenij said: <q>I wish
            to learn whether you are speaking the truth; then I shall let you go; I shall put my
            mark on your face for all time.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m48">
      <p pageref="183r">The maiden Maksimijana also began to entreat him: <q>O light, brilliant sun,
            glorious Devgenij <page>183v</page>, to me have come many tsars and kings, brave and
            strong in much strength, but no one has dishonored me with a single word;</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m49">
      <p pageref="183v">
         <q>all have been conquered by my hands.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m50">
      <p pageref="183v">
         <q>But now God has submitted me to you.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m51">
      <p pageref="183v">
         <q>If you join with me, there will be nothing stronger than we and no one can stand
               <supplied>against us</supplied>.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m52">
      <p pageref="183v">Glorious Devgenij said: <q>Brother, Maksimijana, I have no man's help save
            the grace of God and my mother's prayer: that will help me.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m53">
      <p pageref="183v">For Devgenij it is written: <q>If you join with Maksimijana, his life is
            sixteen years; if he joins with Stratigovna, his life is thirty-six years.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m54">
      <p pageref="183v">
         <supplied>Devgenij</supplied> called loudly for his favorite and said: <q>Go to my father
            and my mother and say to them thus:</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m55">
      <p pageref="183v">
         <q>Rejoice, father and mother mine, that I have defeated Filipap.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m56">
      <p pageref="183v">
         <q>And take <supplied>him</supplied> to my father and Maksimijana here to my mother. If you
            offend her with even a single word, this day you cease to live.</q>
      </p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m57">
      <p pageref="183v">The favorite came to his <supplied>Devgenij's</supplied> father's and
         mother's house and brought them Filipap and the maiden Maksimijana and told them all in
         order.</p>
   </anchor>
   <anchor ref="m58">
      <p pageref="183v">His father and mother were ever very joyful about him.</p>
   </anchor>
</root>
